<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Sean Vig's 2011 GSOC Project]]></title>
  <link href="http://flacjacket.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://flacjacket.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-02T22:27:01-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://flacjacket.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sean Vig]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moved to GitHub Pages (Here!)]]></title>
    <link href="http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2014/07/02/moved-to-github-pages-here/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-02T22:07:25-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2014/07/02/moved-to-github-pages-here</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well, I&rsquo;ve moved my <a href="https://seanvig.blogspot.com/">old blog</a> here, to my
<a href="https://pages.github.com/">GitHub pages</a> page.  I&rsquo;ve done this for several
reasons, many of which are mirrored accross the web, but in short, being able
to hack at my blog generator is great.  Integration of nice Jekyll plugins to
deal with things like syntax highlighting, being able to write in Markdown,
easy inclusion of MathJax, being able to write blog posts in vim, the list goes
on.  I haven&rsquo;t really done any configuration, for the most part, I dropped in
the default <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a> configuration with minimal
changes to get my name everywhere and imported my old blog (which included
going in and adding Markdown syntax to all the files, ick). That stuff can all
be pulled from the
<a href="https://github.com/flacjacket/flacjacket.github.io/tree/source">source branch</a>
of my pages branch.</p>

<p>I realize I haven&rsquo;t done anything with this blog in a long time, but maybe I
can put up some new stuff I&rsquo;ve been hacking on now that I&rsquo;ve got this new page.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Finishing What I Started]]></title>
    <link href="http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2012/01/22/finishing-what-i-started/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-22T00:57:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2012/01/22/finishing-what-i-started</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As of today, I&rsquo;m happy to report that my last pull request for angular momentum
coupling was merged into master. The master branch now has the capability to do
arbitrary angular momentum coupling and uncoupling. I ended up writing a
summary of the algorithm I used to write this, which I briefly described (or
more accurately, brushed over) in the previous blog post, the write up for
which is currently hosted on github
<a href="https://github.com/flacjacket/coupling_algorithm">here</a>. This should be all of
the big changes for the angular momentum algebra I can foresee in the near
future.</p>

<p>At this point, school is starting back up again and especially since I have
joined a research group I won&rsquo;t be doing anything big in the near future. That
said, I do have a couple things I&rsquo;ve started in on that I will try to finish up
if I can get some time. First, I started working on some changes to the quantum
printing framework. I have a pull request open for some new tests to the
quantum printing framework, so if that can get finished up I&rsquo;ll try to work
on getting those changes in. This was an issue that had been brought up
before (around the time I started the GSoC project) and even the work I&rsquo;ve done
so far, I&rsquo;ve dug up a couple issues with the printing framework. The current
pull for the tests are <a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/908">here</a> and the
changes to the printing framework which are to follow are
<a href="https://github.com/flacjacket/sympy/tree/quantum_printing">here</a>.</p>

<p>In addition, over winter break, I dug into some related issues with Piecewise,
particularly with the treatment of the otherwise parameter. Just today I opened
a pull request for collecting feedback on the changes I made
<a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/1009">here</a>.</p>

<p>Now that the spin stuff is finished, I&rsquo;ve been thinking about going back and
looking at the stuff I did at the beginning of the GSoC project, particularly
some of the stuff with CG coefficients and simplification of these terms. From
what I remember, there should be some quick changes to make some stuff run much
better, so if I get time, I&rsquo;ll take a look back at that.</p>

<p>Last, while I am quite happy with how the current angular momentum coupling and
uncoupling methods treat numerical cases, there&rsquo;s nothing really there for
treating symbolic cases and any symbolic arguments cause the methods to return
a very general summation. I put some thought into modifying the current
algorithm to allow for some forms of symbolic coupling and uncoupling, but I
wasn&rsquo;t able to come up with any. If I can sit down and find something that
could do symbolic coupling and uncoupling, that would be the icing on the cake
of the current algorithm.</p>

<p>With the merging of this pull request, everything that I set out to do for my
GSoC project last summer has been completed in some form.  There may be some
things to refine or work on, but for the most part, I have accomplished
everything I set out to do. Unless I make some big changes to the coupling
algorithm, like working out something with symbolic cases, or make some other
big change to the angular momentum algebra, this will likely be my last post
here, at least until something else comes up that I&rsquo;d like to document.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Finalizing Arbitrary Spin Coupling]]></title>
    <link href="http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/11/27/finalizing-arbitrary-spin-coupling/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-27T23:21:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/11/27/finalizing-arbitrary-spin-coupling</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As expected, my work with Sympy slowed drastically once school started, but
nevertheless, I have found enough time to polish off the coupling of arbitrary
number of spin spaces that I started over the summer. I&rsquo;ll probably wait until
after school is done (and the initial Google Code-In traffic dies down) before
opening a pull request, but it has neared the state of conclusion, but I will
outline the work done on the branch <a href="https://github.com/flacjacket/sympy/tree/multi_coupled">here</a>.</p>

<p>A notable change from the summer is the coupling and uncoupling code is now
<em>much</em> cleaner. The old methods used messy <code>while True</code> loops which would
increment some parameters and check if some end condition was reached, which I
found very unsatisfactory and open to some weird use case throwing it into
complete disarray. The new methods utilize the notion that any coupling or
uncoupling will occur such that there is a well defined change in either the j
(in the case of coupling) or m (in the case of uncoupling) values from their
maximal values, and this change can be applied over the (un)couplings in the
same way you can distribute n balls in m boxes, then it is just matching an
integer to a given state and check that the given state is physically feasible.</p>

<p>In addition, I have added all necessary documentation for the new functionality
and fixed a few other minor issues with other parts of the new code. I may yet
change some of the handling of the j_coupling parameter, but I will reevaluate
that when I have more time to look at the code after I finish the semester.</p>

<p>The passing of quantum numbers to define the couplings and un-couplings is
still quite verbose, but I see no better way of passing the parameters,
hopefully in review someone will see a better way of defining states and
couplings.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Finishing GSoC]]></title>
    <link href="http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/08/19/finishing-gsoc/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-19T23:37:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/08/19/finishing-gsoc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So this is the last week of the GSoC program. I&rsquo;ll be writing up a full report
on what I&rsquo;ve done over the summer
<a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/wiki/GSoC-2011-Report-Sean-Vig">here</a> and it
will be updated over this next week. This blog post will be recapping this last
week of progress and looking forward past the GSoC.</p>

<p>The main thing to report with this last week was the finishing the work on the
spin coupling work that was laid out last week and the writing of the code for
Coupled spin states, the last pull request I&rsquo;ll get in during the GSoC project
is currently open and should only need a last bit of code review to get pulled.</p>

<p>The main thing now is moving beyond the work that will be done during the GSoC
project. While I&rsquo;ll be starting classes this next week and I have my qual the
next week, so work will definitely slow down. However, this last week, I worked
on the multi_coupling branch, which takes the coupling work that is in the
current pull and expands it to allow for an arbitrary number of spin bases. The
first thing to implement with this was a means of representing the coupling
between the spin bases, since the order in which spaces are coupled matters. To
do this, I added a jcoupling option to the functions that deal with coupled
states. It currently seems pretty messy, but I&rsquo;m not sure of a better way to do
it, as coupling multiple spaces will just pick up a bunch of additional quantum
numbers that need to be represented somehow. Basically, this parameter is
passed as a list of lists, where each element of the outermost list represents
a coupling between two spin spaces. These inner lists have 3 elements, 2 giving
the number of the space that is being coupled and the third being the j value
of these spaces coupled together.  For example, if we wanted to represent a
state $|j,m,j_1,j_2,(j_{12}),j_3\rangle$, the jcoupling would be <code>( (1,2,j12),
)</code>. If this option is not set, then the methods default to coupling the spaces
in numerical order, i.e. 1 and 2, then 1,2 and 3, etc.  Using this, I have been
able to rewrite the uncouple code. The results do not yet have tests, and I&rsquo;ll
definitely need to do some calculations by hand to make sure this is working
properly, but looking at it, I am pretty confident in the results, tho the code
could use some cleaning up.</p>

<p>Moving forward from this would be to get the couple method working with
arbitrary spin spaces and run through all of the functions that deal with spin
coupling and make sure nothing is still hard coded to use two spin bases. Other
than that, the project that I&rsquo;d set out to work on has been basically
completed. I&rsquo;ll continue to work with and develop sympy when I have some spare
and hopefully continue to add features and functionality to the quantum module.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Coupled_spin Merged]]></title>
    <link href="http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/08/12/getting-coupledspin-merged/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-12T20:50:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/08/12/getting-coupledspin-merged</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The biggest development this week was working out what is needed to get the
coupled_spin which implements spin coupling merged back into master. There were
some things to clean up with non-spin modules and a few minor things to
address, but in cleaning this up, there will be some big changes to the way
spin coupling works. First, with respect to things that have been implemented,
rewrite and represent will no longer handle the coupling and uncoupling of
states. To do coupling and uncoupling, instead, a couple and uncouple method
will be created to handle the coupling and uncoupling of states. In addition,
coupled states will now be represented by new classes, J?KetCoupled for the
Cartesian directions. These will be returned by rewrite when a TensorProduct is
coupled and will return the proper vector for the coupled space when it is
represented and can be uncoupled when an uncoupled operator acts on it.</p>

<p>Most of these new changes have been implemented to varying degrees. There is
some functionality lacking, but much of what remains for this is to implement
tests for the new functions and make sure everything is working properly.</p>

<p>The coupling of arbitrary number of spin spaces had made slow progress due to
some ambiguity when coupled states were created using normal states, but with
the new Coupled classes, specifying the coupling should be possible, thus
making the computations easier.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Moving Beyond First Coupling Iteration]]></title>
    <link href="http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/08/05/moving-beyond-first-coupling-iteration/"/>
    <updated>2011-08-05T19:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/08/05/moving-beyond-first-coupling-iteration</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the last week, one of the main things I did was to submit a pull request for
the coupled spin machinery that I have been working on. This pull request can
be seen <a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/524">here</a>. This
implements the coupling and uncoupling operations for states and operators and
how these states and operators interact for coupling of two spin states. This
pull still has some kinks to work out and some details to iron out, but should
be finished up soon.</p>

<p>Moving beyond this pull, the rest of this week has been in working on modifying
the coupling methods developed in this pull and making them work for an
arbitrary number of spin spaces. The current idea will be to pass a tuple of j
values which are to be coupled instead of passing j1 and j2 parameters. While
this would work, it would be nice to be able to define how the terms are
coupled, noting that the order of how the spaces are coupled matter in
determining the coefficients and what will be diagonal in the basis of the
coupled states. The current way I am working the coupling is to couple j1 and
j2, then couple this to j3, etc. I have currently changed the all the methods
to accept the tuple of j values, however, the coupling and uncoupling methods
have not been changed to accept arbitrary numbers of spaces. Most of this week
has been thinking and trying to determine a good way to implement this
machinery that scales to arbitrary numbers of spaces. While it is not directly
necessary for dealing with spin states, I will likely also implement
Wigner-6j/9j/12j coefficients in cg.py, which will be very similar to the
Wigner-3j symbols that were implemented with the Clebsch-Gordan coefficients.</p>

<p>While I am starting to work on this final component of my project, it will be a
close call as to whether or not it can get pushed in time to make it in before
the end of the project, which will be in just 2 weeks. The initial coupling
stuff should get in, but this will be a much closer call. That said, I will
definitely see this last part of the project into master.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Finishing Current Coupled Spin Work]]></title>
    <link href="http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/07/30/finishing-current-coupled-spin-work/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-30T03:45:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/07/30/finishing-current-coupled-spin-work</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This last week I made some good headway towards finishing up the coupled spin
state work for the coupling of two spin spaces. The decision was made that
spin states should not contain any information as to their coupling, which
greatly simplifies not only the code, but also the allowable cases when it
comes doing things such as applying operators, rewriting, etc. As such, I am
very close to finalizing this stage in the coupled spin work. I will try to fix
up the implementation for some symbolic cases that should be doable under the
current implementation, but all the current code has tests implemented and
docstrings in place, so a pull request will be coming up shortly.</p>

<p>With this stage finishing, I will be moving on to generalizing the current
implementation to coupling between more than two spin spaces. I will first need
to expand cg.py to include Wigner-6j/9j/etc symbols to describe the coupling
between these additional spaces. The logic for spin states will need to be
reworked as well, not only to implement these new terms for coupling additional
spin spaces, but most of the logic will need to be reworked to allow for an
arbitrary number of coupled spin spaces.</p>

<p>While the change to get rid of what would be considered a coupled spin state
(that is a state where the state has defined the coupled spaces) does simplify
the current implementation, it does limit what can be done. For example, an
uncoupled operator could not be applied to a coupled state, as the coupled
states would need to be uncoupled, which is only possible if the j values of
the coupled states is known. However it was suggested by Brian that a new class
be created to deal with coupled states in this sense. Time permitting, I will
begin to look at the possibility of implementing such a feature into the
current spin framework.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Improving Rewrite and Represent for Coupled/uncoupled States]]></title>
    <link href="http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/07/22/improving-rewrite-and-represent-for/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-22T19:30:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/07/22/improving-rewrite-and-represent-for</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This last week, most of the coding I have done has been working on getting
represent working properly for coupled and uncoupled states. After doing a
quick double check on what the basis vectors of a coupled or uncoupled state
would be, I was able to get this code in. Tests for the represent logic will
still need to be added, but so far it seems to be working properly.</p>

<p>In addition, I modified the rewrite logic to implement the represent method.
This way all of the coupling and uncoupling logic is taken care of by
represent, just as the represent method also takes care of all rotations of
coordinate bases. To simplify the rewrite logic, I also implemented a
vect_to_state, which returns a linear combination of states given any state
vector when provided with the appropriate parameters, to specify coupled or
uncoupled and what the j1 and j2 parameters are.</p>

<p>In addition to this work, I also wrote up the shell of the class that would
handle tensor products of operators. However, in its current state, it doesn&rsquo;t
function as one would expect, as the <code>_apply_operator_*</code> methods are not being
called by qapply. This, in addition to noting that there is very little logic
that is in the TensorProductState class has been making me think I can move
most of the logic for states and operators that are uncoupled out of the spin
class, implementing it instead in places like qapply and represent.  The only
trick would be the uncoupled$\rightarrow$coupled logic, which is just about the only
bit of logic that the TensorProductState class has that couldn&rsquo;t necessarily be
generalized, and the loss of the j1/j2/m1/m2 properties. I will be trying to do
this in the coming week, which will in turn fix the problems I am having with
getting tensor products of states to work.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Developing Coupled/uncoupled States and Operators]]></title>
    <link href="http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/07/16/developing-coupleduncoupled-states-and/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-16T02:31:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/07/16/developing-coupleduncoupled-states-and</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Most of this last week was spent developing coupled and uncoupled states,
beginning to develop how operators will act on these states and writing tests
to ensure the code returns the desired result. This week I finished up writing
the code for expressing states, and the logic for rewriting from one to the
other and back. In addition to this, I implemented the tests which are used for
these rewrites. This mostly finishes up the logic for the coupled/uncoupled
states, there is still the represent logic which may need to be implemented,
tho this will take some looking into to determine what is appropriate and
necessary to implement.</p>

<p>For the operators, using the qapply logic already in place, I have begun to
implement how operators act on coupled and uncoupled states. I have thus far
only implemented logic for coupled operators, that is, for example $J_z =
J_{z_1} + J_{z_2}$ ($=J_{z_1} \otimes 1 + 1 \otimes J_{z_2}$ in an
uncoupled representation). In addition to defining how uncoupled product states
are acted upon by spin operators, I have expanded those already implemented
methods to act on arbitrary states, as they had only previously been defined in
how they act on JzKet&rsquo;s. This was done by defining a basis, such that, with the
now improved rewrite logic, any state can be rewritten into an appropriate
basis for the state and the state in then acted upon by the operator. I have
begun to implement the tests that ensure the implemented logic is valid in all
cases, both numerical and symbolic, tho this is still a work in progress.</p>

<p>The focus for this next week will be continuing the development of the spin
operators, hopefully getting to working with uncoupled spin operators, i.e.
operators given in a tensor product to only act on one of the uncoulped states,
and developing the tests necessary to the implementation of these states. If I
can complete this, I will be closing in on the completion of the coupling of
two spin spaces.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Cleaning Up Simplification and Moving Into Coupled States]]></title>
    <link href="http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/07/08/cleaning-up-simplification-and-moving/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-08T21:40:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/07/08/cleaning-up-simplification-and-moving</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So, as I stated in my last post, the first thing I dealt with was fixing up the
<code>_cg_simp_add</code> method by implementing pattern matching and move the logic for
determining if the simplification can be performed and performing the
simplification out of the <code>_cg_simp_add</code> method and developing a system that
can easily be expanded to include additional simplifications. To do this, I
created another method, <code>_check_cg_simp</code>, which takes various expression to
determine if the sum can be simplified. Using Wild variables, the method takes
an expression which is matched to the terms of the sum. The method uses a list
to store the terms in the sum which can be simplified, so additional
expressions are used to determine the length of the list and the index of the
items that are matched.  There are also additional parameters to handle the
leading terms and the sign of the terms. There are still some issues with this
method, as when there is more than 1 Clebsch-Gordan coefficient in the sum,
then the leading term cannot be matched on the term.</p>

<p>In addition to the finishing of this component of the Clebsch-Gordan
coefficient simplification, I have started into working on the coupled spin
states and the methods to rewrite them in coupled and uncoupled bases. Coupled
spin states are set by passing j1 and j2 parameters when creating the state,
for example:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span>  <span class="n">JzKet</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">j1</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">j2</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="o">|</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">j1</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">j2</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="o">&gt;</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>These states can be given in the uncoupled basis using the rewrite method and
passing coupled=False, so:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="n">JzKet</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">j1</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="n">j2</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">rewrite</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">Jz</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">coupled</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="bp">False</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">2</span><span class="o">**</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">*|</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="o">|</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="o">&gt;/</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="o">**</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">*|</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="o">|</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="o">&gt;/</span><span class="mi">2</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>This can also be done with a normal state and passing j1 and j2
parameters to the rewrite method, as:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="n">JzKet</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">rewrite</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">Jz</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">j1</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">j2</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">2</span><span class="o">**</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">*|</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="o">|</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="o">&gt;/</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="o">**</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="o">/</span><span class="mi">2</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">*|</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="o">&gt;</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="o">|</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="o">&gt;/</span><span class="mi">2</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>How the coupled states will be handled by rewrite still needs to be addressed,
but that will need some thinking and with another GSoC project doing a lot of
changes to the represent function, it may take some coordination to get this
and the TensorProducts of states and operators working.</p>

<p>Note that in the python expressions above, the states are given as uncoupled
states written as tensor products. Uncoupled states will be written as
TensorProduct&rsquo;s of states, which will be extended later to spin operators,
being written in the uncoupled basis as a TensorProduct. I&rsquo;ve just started
playing with the uncoupled states and the various methods that will be used to
go from uncoupled to coupled states and I&rsquo;ve been putting them in a separate
TensorProductState class, which subclasses TensorProduct, which keeps all the
spin logic separate from the main TensorProduct class, tho this will have to be
expanded to include operators. Developing the logic for these uncoupled spin
states will be the primary focus of this next week of
coding.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Continuing GSoC Work]]></title>
    <link href="http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/07/02/continuing-gsoc-work/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-02T12:27:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/07/02/continuing-gsoc-work</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This last week, I have made progress on my project working on laying the base
work for the spin states and in reimplementing logic in the <code>cg_simp</code> method
for Clebsch-Gordan coefficients.</p>

<p>First, I have started the work on the implementation of coupled/uncoupled spin
states. Currently, this is implemented by adding a <code>coupled</code> property to the
spin states. This can be set to True for coupled, False for uncoupled or left
as None for other states. As this evolves, I will move to having uncoupled
product states be represented by a TensorProduct of two spin states. The next
key will be establishing represent and rewrite logic for these spin states.
Part of this will be figuring out how exactly these methods will work and what
they will return. Namely, the represent method, noting that when representing
an uncoupled state as a coupled state, it returns states with multiple j
values, which under the current logic, would return matrices of different
dimension. Also, we will have to determine what represent will do to uncoupled
tensor product spin states. This next week, I will likely rebase this branch
against the CG branch so I can start using the Clebsch-Gordan coefficients to
implement these functions as the CG pull is finalized.</p>

<p>With the Clebsch-Gordan coefficients, this last week I was able to get the
simplification of symbolic Sum objects working. I did this using the pattern
matching built into sympy with Wild and .match. The final step with this should
be to rework the logic of <code>_cg_simp_add</code> to make it easier to add in additional
symmetries.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Transitioning to Spin States]]></title>
    <link href="http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/06/25/transitioning-to-spin-states/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-25T04:18:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/06/25/transitioning-to-spin-states</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This last week, the first thing that was taken care of was finishing the x/y/z
spin basis representation. Having fixed the Wigner small d-function in the
Rotation class, the tests for this were put into the pull request and the pull
was merged into the sympy master, making this my first pull request since
starting GSoC. There is still some changes that will come for the Rotation
class, namely the creation of a symbolic WignerD class which is returned by the
current Rotation.D and Rotation.d functions, but that will be dealt with in a
later pull request.</p>

<p>With the x/y/z basis stuff finally out of the way, I moved back to getting the
Glebsch-Gordan coefficient/Wigner-3j symbols to a state where they can be
pulled. Having fallen behind in getting the CG coefficient simplification to a
suitable state and with the work on the x/y/z spin basis pushing the timeline
back even further, the current goal is to merge what I have so far and move on
to the coupled spin states. What I have so far is the classes for the Wigner-3j
symbols and the Clebsch-Gordan coefficients which can be manipulated
symbolically and evaluated, and a very rough version of the cg_simp method.
Currently, this method can handle 3 numerical simplification, however the code
is still messy and having more cases would be ideal. That said, in an effort to
make sure the key parts of this GSoC project are covered, I&rsquo;ll be moving into
writing the coupled spin states.</p>

<p>For the spin states portion of this project, I will develop a means of writing
coupled and uncoupled spin states. The uncoupled product basis states will be
written using the TensorProduct, which is in the current quantum module; each
of the states in the tensor product will be states as they are currently
implemented. To represent coupled basis spin states, the current spin states
will be modified to included a coupled parameter. This value stores the J_i&rsquo;s
of the spin spaces which are being coupled. In addition to the spin states
being implemented, methods will be written to utilize the CG coefficients
mentioned earlier to go between coupled and uncoupled basis representation.
Look for more next week as this code is fleshed out.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[More CG Simplification and Wrapping Up X/y/z Spin Bases]]></title>
    <link href="http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/06/18/more-cg-simplification-and-wrapping-up/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-18T10:17:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/06/18/more-cg-simplification-and-wrapping-up</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For the first part of this last week, I continued on my work to get sums of
Clebsch-Gordan coefficients to simplify. Using the same general logic that I
outlined in the last blog entry, besides general cleaning up of the code, most
of the work at the beginning of the week was spent on trying to develop a
function that could check an expression for CG coefficients matching a set of
conditions.</p>

<p>The rationale behind trying to write such a method is that it would make it
much easier to identify the times where symmetries could be utilized. With
such a method, the process of checking for CG coefficients could be done in a
single function and the logic for implementing CG symmetries could be handled
in this one function. The current method uses lists of tuples to specify the
conditions on CG coefficients. For example, if the j1 value of a CG coefficient
needed to be =0, you could pass the tuple (&ldquo;j1&rdquo;,0), or if the m1 and m3 values
match (&ldquo;m1&rdquo;,&ldquo;m3&rdquo;). All the conditions for each CG coefficient are combined into
a single tuple. The current snag with simplifications of sums of products of CG
coefficients. For example:
$$ \sum_{\alpha,\beta} C_{\alpha\beta}^{c\gamma} C_{\alpha\beta}^{c&#8217;\gamma&#8217;}
= \delta_{cc&#8217;} \delta_{\gamma\gamma&#8217;} $$</p>

<p>While the current method would be able to check for specific values on the CG
coefficients, I have yet to come up with a good way to check that the m1 and m2
values are the same when they can take any value, as in this example. As it
stands, this code still seems like quite a hack and will need some work before
it is good to go.</p>

<p>What is left with this part of the project is:</p>

<ul>
<li>Getting simplification to work with sums of products of terms (as in the example above)</li>
<li>Applying CG symmetries to perform simplifications</li>
<li>Simplification of symbolic CG sums</li>
<li>Fixing up the printing of CG terms</li>
<li>Final testing/documentation</li>
</ul>


<p>This part of the project has unfortunately fallen behind the preliminary
schedule by a bit, as it was due to be finished up last week. I&rsquo;ll outline what
I&rsquo;m currently working on finish up next, but hopefully I can finish the CG
stuff ASAP so I can move on to working on the spin stuff which is the true meat
of the project and try to get back on schedule.</p>

<p>After meeting with my project mentor, Ondrej, on Wednesday, it was decided that
the focus would shift to finishing up the work I&rsquo;d started on x/y/z spin bases
and representation of spin states that I&rsquo;d started before GSoC had officially
started.</p>

<p>The first order of business was identifying an error in the Wigner small-d
function, which is used extensively in the changing of spin bases. With Ondrej
noting that the small-d function was defined only on a small interval and then
me discovering the bug in the Rotation.d method, we were able to address this.
However, no sooner had this been done than Ondrej is able to work out a better
equation for the small-d function, which will likely replace the current
implementation.</p>

<p>Other than this, most of the work this week on the x/y/z basis representation
was in documentation, testing and generally cleaning up the code to be pulled.
The current pull request (my first work to be submitted since the start of
GSoC) is still open <a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/pull/431">here</a>.  While
this pull integrates the current work on basis representation, after this pull
there is still some work that will need to be done testing both the Wigner
small-d and the D functions, for both symbolic and numerical values, and
ensuring they return the correct results. Because the representation code
relies so heavily on these functions, it is imperative that these functions
evaluate properly. Once these are fully tested, there will also likely need to
be more tests to ensure all the representation code returns the right values
for as many odd cases as would be necessary to test. Hopefully I can finish
this up soon and move on to other work that still needs to be done.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[More Improvements to the Simplification Method]]></title>
    <link href="http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/06/11/more-improvements-to-simplification/"/>
    <updated>2011-06-11T05:59:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/06/11/more-improvements-to-simplification</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was out of town for the beginning of this week, so I don&rsquo;t have as much to
report, nevertheless in the last few days, I have made some good improvements
to the cg_simp method, allowing it to simplify cases other than just the simple
sums, tho it still only handles the same case as before involving the sum of .
While it is entirely possible I&rsquo;m doing something stupid in performing all the
checks, as far as I can tell, it works for the given case. Because the code
itself is not yet very clear and it is not always straightforward what is
happening, I&rsquo;ll explain what I have implemented.</p>

<p>First note that for the simplifications that will be made, it is required to
have a sum of terms. The first for loop in the method constructs two lists
<code>cg_part</code> and <code>other_part</code>, the former consisting of all terms of the sum
containing a CG coefficient and the latter the other terms.</p>

<p>Next, we iterate over the list <code>cg_part</code>. The number of CG coefficients is
computed, which determines which simplifications can be made (currently, the
only implemented simplification uses terms with 1 CG coefficient in each sum
term).  Those terms with the proper number of CG coefficients are then
considered for the simplification. The way this will work is: based on the
properties of the CG coefficient in the term, it will search the rest of the
list for other terms that can be used in the simplification, and if all the
terms exist, will simplify the terms.</p>

<p>Turning to the implementation, when iterating through the list, the first thing
to do is determine the properties of the CG coefficient terms, that is to
extract from the term in the sum the CG coefficient itself and the numerical
leading terms. Here it is also noted the sign of these numerical terms.</p>

<p>Next, the rest of the list is checked to see if a simplification can be made
using the determined term. To keep track of this, a list, <code>cg_index</code>, is
initialized with <code>False</code> as the element of the list. In checking the later
terms, we preform a similar decomposition as with the first term, that is
splitting up the CG coefficient from the other components of the term,
determining the CG coefficient, the leading terms and the sign of the terms. If
the properties of these are correct, then the corresponding element of
<code>cg_index</code> is updated with a tuple <code>(term, cg, coeff)</code> where term is the term
in <code>cg_part</code> (so this element can be removed later), the CG coefficient and the
leading numerical coefficient of the coefficient.</p>

<p>Now, if all the elements of <code>cg_index</code> are changed, the simplification is
preformed. When this happens, first we find the minimum coefficient of the
chosen CG coefficients, which determines the number of times we can apply the
simplification. Then the replacing happens; for each element in <code>cg_index</code>
(which is a tuple) the first element of the tuple is popped off <code>cg_part</code>,
then, if the term is not eliminated by the simplification, a new term is
created and added to <code>cg_part</code>, and finally a constant is added to
<code>other_part</code>, completing the simplification.</p>

<p>Looking at the code, this method is very straightforward, but should be robust
and scalable for treating cases of sums with numerical leading coefficients,
and now that the i&rsquo;s have been dotted and the t&rsquo;s have been crossed on testing
this method, implementing new cases should come rapidly in the next couple
days.  However, one place where this will still need some work is in
implementing symbolic simplification, both in dealing with symbolic leading
terms on the CG coefficients and symbolic CG coefficients themselves. This will
take a bit of thought and likely a bit of help to complete, but this is one
thing I hope to work on in the next week. In addition, as the simplification
comes into place, I&rsquo;ll work on polishing out the last of the details to get the
classes for the Wigner3j/CG coefficients working properly.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Implementing Clebsch-Gordan Symmetries and Sum Properties]]></title>
    <link href="http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/05/31/implementing-clebsch-gordan-symmetries/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-31T08:51:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/05/31/implementing-clebsch-gordan-symmetries</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this first week of the GSoC project, I focused on implementing methods that
would simplify terms with Clebsch-Gordan coefficients. This still has a long
was to go, but I will outline what I have done so far.</p>

<p>The first step was implementing means of dealing with sums of single
coefficients. This would hopefully look something like:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="n">Sum</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">GC</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">a</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">alpha</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">a</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">alpha</span><span class="p">),</span> <span class="p">(</span><span class="n">alpha</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="o">-</span><span class="n">a</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">a</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="mi">2</span><span class="o">*</span><span class="n">a</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="mi">1</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The first implementation of this used an indexing system that was able to index
single coefficients, which could then be processed. This allowed the
simplification function to act properly in simple numerical cases, so it could
do things like:</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
<span class='line-number'>2</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="n">cg_simp</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">CG</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="o">-</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="n">CG</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="n">CG</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">0</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="n">a</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span><span class='line'><span class="n">a</span><span class="o">+</span><span class="mi">3</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>The problem with this implementation is doing something as simple as having one
of the terms have a constant coefficient would break it. In addition, there
would be no clear way to extend this to sums involving products of multiple
Clebsch-Gordan coefficients.</p>

<p>To deal with this, I started working a solution that could deal with having
constant coefficients and products of coefficients. Currently implemented is
method which creates list of tuples containing information about the
Clebsch-Gordan coefficients and the leading coefficients of the Clebsch-Gordan
coefficients. Currently, the only implemented logic is only able to deal with
the case in that could be dealt with in the previous implementation, however,
this should be able to expand to encompass more exotic cases.</p>

<p>Another thing that was touched on this last week was treating symmetries. These
are quite simple to implement, as they need only return new Clebsch-Gordan
coefficients in place of old ones, just with the parameters changed in
correspondence with the symmetry operation. The key will be using these
symmetries to help in simplifying terms. This will be based on the development
of better logic in the simplification method and the implementation of some
means of determining if these symmetries can be used to apply some property of
the Clebsch-Gordan coefficients that can simplify the expression.</p>

<p>I will be out of town this next week on a vacation, and will not be able to get
work in, but I will continue working on this when I return, with the intention
of getting it to a state that can be pushed within the next couple weeks.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Official GSoC Start]]></title>
    <link href="http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/05/25/official-gsoc-start/"/>
    <updated>2011-05-25T00:37:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/05/25/official-gsoc-start</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week marks the official start of the Google Summer of Code. While I
started getting my feet wet last week after finishing the last of my finals and
grading, the bulk of the work has just started turning out. I&rsquo;ll quick cover
what I have from this last week and what I&rsquo;m looking to get working this week.</p>

<p>Before the start, I worked out expanding the functionality of the currently
implemented x/y/z bases, which work I have
<a href="https://github.com/flacjacket/sympy/tree/xyz_bases">here</a>. The previous
implementation only allowed for evaluating inner products between states in the
same basis and representing the states in the Jz basis and then only with j=&frac12;
states. Using the Wigner D-function, implemented with the Rotation class, I
implemented represent to go between the x/y/z bases for any j values. Both
<code>_eval_innerproduct</code> and <code>_rewrite_as</code> were then created to take advantage of the
represent function to extend the functionality of the inner product and to
implement rewrite between any bases and any arbitrary j values.</p>

<p>This seems like this is some documentation and tests away from being pushed,
but there is something buggy with the Rotation.d function, implementing the
Wigner small d-matrix. I noticed when trying to do</p>

<figure class='code'><figcaption><span></span></figcaption><div class="highlight"><table><tr><td class="gutter"><pre class="line-numbers"><span class='line-number'>1</span>
</pre></td><td class='code'><pre><code class='python'><span class='line'><span class="o">&gt;&gt;&gt;</span> <span class="n">qapply</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">JzBra</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">*</span><span class="n">JzKet</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span><span class="o">.</span><span class="n">rewrite</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="s">&#39;Jx&#39;</span><span class="p">)</span>
</span></code></pre></td></tr></table></div></figure>


<p>and I wasn&rsquo;t getting the right answer. As it turns out, the Rotation.d
function, which uses Varshalovich 4.3.2 Eq 7, does not give the right answer
for <code>Rotation.d(1,1,0,-pi/2)</code> or <code>Rotation.d(1,0,1,pi/2)</code>. Namely, there is
something wrong with the equation that doesn&rsquo;t change the sign of the matrix
element when reversing the sign of the beta Euler angle. Running all four
differential representations given by Varshalovich for the small d matrix, Eq
7-10, give the wrong result, so the derivations of these will need to be
checked to fix this. I have a bug report up
<a href="http://code.google.com/p/sympy/issues/detail?id=2423">here</a>.</p>

<p>As for what I will be implementing this week, I already have the basics of the
Wigner3j and CG class implemented, the work for this going up
<a href="https://github.com/flacjacket/sympy/tree/cg_coeff">here</a>. This includes
creating the objects, <em>some</em> of the printing functionality and numerical
evaluation of the elements using the wigner.py functions. The meat of the class
that I&rsquo;m currently working on is the <code>cg_simp</code> function, which will simplify
expressions of Clebsch-Gordan coefficients. I currently have one case working,
that is <code>Sum(CG(a,alpha,0,0,a,alpha),(alpha,-a,a)) == 2a+1</code> which is
Varshalovich 8.7.1 Eq 1. There are still some things to smooth out with the
implementation, but I should have that worked out a bit better, in addition to
some more simplifications by the end of the week.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s all I have for now, watch for updates within the week as to what I&rsquo;ve
gotten done and what I have yet to do.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Best Things in Life Are Free (and Open Source)]]></title>
    <link href="http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/04/25/best-things-in-life-are-free-and-open/"/>
    <updated>2011-04-25T19:02:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://flacjacket.github.io/blog/2011/04/25/best-things-in-life-are-free-and-open</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hi all,</p>

<p>This adventure into blogging is to document the work I will be doing this
summer with <a href="http://sympy.org/">SymPy</a>, an open source symbolic mathematics
library written in Python. The project will be done as a part of the
<a href="http://socghop.appspot.com/">Google Summer of Code</a> program. This summer, I
will be developing a symbolic class for creating Clebsch-Gordan coefficients
and will develop the spin algebra in the existing quantum physics module to
utilize these coefficients. The gory details can be read in my
<a href="https://github.com/sympy/sympy/wiki/GSoC%202011%20Application%20Sean%20Vig">application</a>.
My mentor for this project will be Ondej ertk. The project officially starts
May 24, but I&rsquo;ll be diving in once I finish up the last of my finals May
14.  I will be documenting my progress on the project throughout the summer
through this blog, and anyone interested in this is free to watch for
updates once the project is underway.  All my work will be pushed to
<a href="https://github.com/flacjacket/sympy">my SymPy fork</a> on github.</p>

<p>That&rsquo;s enough for now, I&rsquo;ll be checking back in once I get started in the
summer. Now, back to trying to graduate.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
